In Vietnam, I
Việt Nam Mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni
respectfully address the Buddha Shakyamuni and all fellow practitioners
con Kính bạch cô cùng tất cả các đạo hữu
present at this
có mặt trong buổi lễ tổng kết chương
year-end program summary ceremony. I would like to share my
trình cuối năm 2019 con xin kể câu
professional story. My name is
chuyện chuyên nghiệp của con tên con là
Bui Hoai Vuong, my given name is Tam
Bùi hoài Vương phát danh của con là tâm
Duyen, and I live at house number 680, group 2,
Duyên con ở đại số nhà 680 tổ 2 khu
Trung Son area, Cam Son ward, Cam Pha city, Quang
Trung Sơn phường Cẩm Sơn Cẩm Phả Quảng
Ninh province. From childhood to adulthood, I have been very
Ninh từ bé đến lớn thì là con rất là hay
sick and stayed home to recover. However, when I
bị ốm và ở nhà để con ốm nhưng khi con
went to the hospital, my mother had no illness. My illnesses
đến viện để con mẹ không có bệnh gì cả
usually occurred
mà ốm của con thì thường nó có hai rơi
on the 14th and 15th of the lunar month, and on the 30th and 1st of the lunar month. There
vào ngày 14 15 và ngày 30 mùng một cũng
was a time when I had to eat
có một thời gian để con lại phải ăn chay
vegetarian food, and another time when I ate meat.
sống cũng có một thời gian con ăn mặn
In 2008, I got married, and on December
lúc 2008 là con đã lập gia đình rồi và
20th, I moved to a house on the land where I am currently
20 12 là con ở cái tại mảnh đất con đang
living. My husband cut down a
ở đấy thì là chồng con có cưa cây phát
tree in front of the house. Before knowing about Buddhism, after he
biết về Phật pháp thì sau khi mà cơ cây
finished cutting down the tree, I experienced a
phát càng ở trước cửa nhà xong thì là
frostbite, and my father and
con có bị băng giá và bố đẻ của con và
husband took me
chồng đã đưa con
to a shelter.  The electricity was very strong in Hai
ở một cái cửa điện rất là lớn ở Hải
Duong, I couldn't conveniently go up there. At
Dương con không tiện lên cây này đây thì
that time, I was like a frozen mother, I didn't
làm lúc đấy là con mẹ Băng Giá con không
know what was happening, but when I got there, the
biết cái gì đã rồi thì đã đến đấy thì
shaman threw me out, and it also happened on the 15th and 1st day of the lunar month.
được thầy chục văng ra và cũng rơi vào
It only happened on the 15th and
ngày rằm Mùng Một đó là chỉ quanh quẩn
1st day of the lunar month, not on
mỗi ngày rằm Mùng 1 mà không rơi vào
other days, even when I had surgery, it
những ngày khác kể cả những lần con mổ
always happened on the 15th and
hạnh nghĩa là gì đều rơi vào ngày rằm
1st day of Tet. I also wondered
Mùng Một Tết và con cũng thắc mắc là tại
why it only happened on those days.
sao nó chỉ rơi vào những ngày đấy Mà
I wasn't affected on other days because
những ngày khác con không bị vì những
I was very healthy, but on
ngày thường con rất là khỏe nhưng cứ rơi
those days, my personality changed completely.
và ngày đấy thì tâm tính một con nó trở
After going to the temple for treatment, I became a fool. I did
thành một người khác sau khi về cửa điện
n't know anything anymore, and I was standing
người ngố Con không biết gì nữa và đứng
in the middle of the road, almost like a car avoiding
ở giữa đường thì gần như là ô tô tránh
me, but I didn't know how to avoid it. It took me
to như con không biết đường tránh đưa
about 23 months later, I was still a
tôi đến tầm khoảng 23 tháng sau thì con
little more lucid, then I met a shaman.
một chút thì con gặp được một thầy pháp
I also had a wish to
thì con cũng là con có tâm nguyện con
worship Buddha, so the shaman set up an incense burner for me to worship Buddha at
thờ Phật thầy bốc bát hương thờ Phật tại
home from 2012 to 2018.
gia cho con từ 2012 đến 2018
I asked him for his help.  I've been using an incense burner to worship
em là con xin thỉnh bát hương để thờ
Buddha at home for six years. For
Phật tại gia trong vòng 6 năm đấy Thì cứ
about three months, I'm healthy, and for the other three months, I'm sick and
tầm 3 tháng con khỏe 3 tháng còn lại úng
fall into a state of depression. I
và con rơi vào trạng thái trầm cảm xong
work hard, but I ca
lòng này thì con làm việc vất vả nhưng
n't sleep at night. Everyone else
cứ đến đêm con không ngủ được mọi người
goes to sleep, and even when I drink carrot juice, I ca
đi ngủ con uống cà rốt ngủ con cũng
n't sleep. I take an
không ngủ được và một ngày của con uống
average of twenty-something
bình quân có thể đến hai mươi mấy viên
pills a day, mostly traditional medicine. But every time I finish a
thuốc toàn là thuốc đông y thôi nhưng cứ
pill, I get sick again. I might get
hát thuốc cả con lại ốm hết thuốc có thể
sick and die on the 14th, 15th, 30th, or 1st of the lunar month.
ốm và cút rơi vào ngày 14 15 30 mùng 1
If I'm not sick, my husband takes a lot of medicine,
nếu con không ốm thì chồng con uống cấp
or I need emergency treatment.
ký hoặc con có đúng cấp cứu nó cứ liên
It's been
tục nó có lặp đi lặp lại trong vòng mấy
like this for years. My father took me to the
năm như thế bố con cũng đưa con đến bệnh
Channel 12 hospital, and they
viện kênh 12 con cũng đi xem thì người
told me I needed to open a shrine or
ta bảo con là phải mở điện mở phủ thì
perform some kind of ritual. I
con phải trả lễ cái gì đấy thì con mới
asked them about it, but I said, "Nowadays, many people follow
hỏi nhưng con bảo bây giờ nhiều người đi
Buddhism and they don't have to offer sacrifices or burn paper money, yet
theo Phật người ta có phải cúng đốt vàng
they're still healthy and
mã thì đâu mà người ta vẫn cứ khỏe mạnh
normal." I decided
bình thường để con cưng quyết là con
against opening a shrine or performing any rituals. But if I had the
không có mờ điện mở phủ con mà nếu có
money,
tiền mà
I'd spend hundreds of millions of dong on it.  I should have
Em ngủ mấy trăm triệu đấy thì phải đi
done better volunteer work and signed up for
làm công quả tốt hơn và ký được nhiều
more lives. I resolutely refused to
mảnh đời hơn cả con cương quyết không đi
follow him. After 65 days, things became
theo xong cái thời gian 65 đấy thì nó
complicated, with constant problems.
công phức xảy ra các tình trạng liên
Sometimes I was lucid, sometimes delirious. My husband and children
miên Lúc thì tỉnh lúc thì mê chồng con
always looked down on me and called me
luôn luôn coi thường và gọi con là con
crazy. Even on the 45th day, they kept calling me
điên cứng ngày mới 45 ngày toàn gọi con
crazy, cursing me, and insulting me.
là con điên chửi là con con điên xúc tại
I didn't want it to be like that,
mà lăng mạ có mà em không muốn như thế
so I couldn't control
nên em không điều khiển là cái hành vi
my behavior. Now I'm in this state, and I'm suffering so much. At
của mình mà bây giờ em bị như này em rất
night, sometimes my
là khổ thì đến lúc mà đêm đến thì cứ lúc
husband and children want to leave me, but I do
thì chồng con muốn bỏ con thì con lại
n't want to, and sometimes I want to leave him. It just keeps falling into these extreme
không muốn bỏ lúc thì con lại muốn bỏ
states. My
chồng con nó cứ rơi và các trọng trạng
husband and I almost
thái là hai vợ chồng con gần như đã thù
hate each other. My children are constantly sick and in critical condition. I
ghét nhau rồi con cái con ốm đau cấp cứu
take a lot of medicine, but
liên miên con uống thuốc cũng rất là
nothing helps. Then, during the time my husband became so
nhiều không hề khỏi mà đến cái thời gian
depressed that he took me
anh trầm cảm đến mức Mở bố đẻ con đưa
to a psychiatric hospital (Channel
con về bệnh viện tâm thần bệnh viện kênh
12) to take medicine. I said, "
12 uống thuốc thì con bảo con vào đây
I'm not sick here, I'm just scared." I wanted to go
con có bị bệnh đâu phải con sợ là con đi
home, but my father took me to temples
về thì bố con lại đưa đến những cửa điện
to watch the rituals and pray. Every time he performed the rituals...  10
để xem cúng lạy cúng mỗi lần cúng 10
million, 15 million VND helped for a while,
triệu 15 triệu được một thời gian con
then I got better, but then I kept having to perform rituals and offerings
lại đỡ đỡ xong con lại bị để cúng cúng
without getting better. Later,
liên miên mãi mà không đỡ về sau thì
on July 8th,
đừng nhân duyên đến ngày mùng 8 tháng 7
2018, a friend kept
năm 2018 thì là con đường một bạn bạn cứ
inviting me to Ba Vang Temple. That day I
rủ con về chùa Ba Vàng Thì hôm đấy con
went,
về thì con cũng được nhân viên con về
and I listened to Buddhist teachings.
chùa và con là nghe học phật pháp để con
I think I benefited from some spiritual aspect,
bò sát này chắc là con có lợi về phần âm
or maybe I had some heavy karma, especially in
hay là con có nghiệp gì đấy nặng nhất là
2018 when I was possessed by a spirit. I went
năm 2018 là con bị vong nhá rất là lặng
to the temple to receive guidance
con về chùa để con được một sự chỉ dạy
from the master and the main Dharma
của xương và đạo tràng chính Thuận thì
assembly. Then, at home, they set up an altar for me to pray for my soul's salvation for 49 days at my home and with my father. During those
trong vòng tu tập 49 ngày thì
49 days of practice, I gradually changed,
số 49 ngày Là con chuyển dần chuyển dần
and with the guidance of the master and the main
và được sự chỉ dạy của trên thầy cùng
Dharma assembly,
với lại đạo tràng chính vận trợ duyên
my family is now
cho gia đình con đến bây giờ thì con
healthier, and my work
được khỏe mạnh hơn và công việc của con
and my daughter's family are no longer
và con gái trong gia đình nó không xảy
experiencing conflicts. And what day
ra những chuyện lục đục như và cái này
is the full moon of the seventh lunar month?  On the
Rằm tháng bảy là ngày rằm mấy ngày mùng
1st of the lunar month, my child was much healthier.
1 nữa và con có khỏe mạnh hơn rất là
Then, on the 1st of the lunar month,
nhiều thế là vào ngày rằm Mùng 1 thì em
the symptoms completely disappeared. This started in
đã chấm dứt hết cái hiện tượng đó từ khi
July of last year. Gradually, over
nào tháng 7 năm vừa rồi dần dần dần dần
time, as I practiced and
rất là cứ thời gian con tu tập tăng giật
increased my spiritual activity, my illnesses
lên kia lạc các bệnh của con nó cứ giảm
gradually decreased. Before, I used to
dần giảm dần đi và con trước đây con hay
see the halos, but now I don't see them
nhìn thấy vòng nhưng giờ con không nhìn
anymore. It's truly amazing! Congratulations!
thấy nữa hả Thật là C3 Chúc mừng em Kính
Dear fellow practitioners, it's true that everything stems
thưa các quý đạo hữu Đúng là cái gì cũng
from karma.
là nghiệp mà ra cái gì cũng ở nghiệp mà
Whether it's ghosts, depression, or
ra mà nào là Vong gá nào là trầm cảm hay
anything else, everything comes from karma. Through our
cái gì cũng ở nghiệp mà ra cái chúng ta
practice, we can transform our karma. We have
tu tập thì chúng ta sẽ chuyển nghiệp
our own place to rely on.
ở tập của chúng ta lo có chỗ của mình
We say we
lương tượng chúng ta nói là chúng ta
rely on the Three Jewels. We say there's the Dharma Jewel,
lương tựa vào tam bảo thì ta bảo có phạt
but the Sangha
Bảo là chung pháp bảo chung nhưng Tăng
Jewel is separate because each temple has its own way of
Bảo thì riêng vì mỗi chùa mỗi chữ tang
practicing, so the practice and
tu tập có khác nhau cho nên sự tu tập
reliance of each Buddhist is also different.
nương tựa của mỗi phật tử cũng khác nhau
In the scriptures, the Buddha taught that giving is six parts:
trong kinh Đức Phật dạy là bố thí 6 phần
three parts belong to the recipient and three
thì ba phần thuộc về người nhận ý và 3
parts belong to the giver. If the
phần thuộc về người bố thí Nếu người
recipient has already...  Rossi's path of complete detachment and non-attachment
nhận thí mà đã hoàn toàn vô tâm vô sân
means that the person making the offering,
của Rossi thì người cúng dường là người
with a pure and respectful heart and
mà với tâm thanh tịnh cung kính và vật
offering pure things,
cúng dường là vật Thanh Tịnh thì mình
receives great merit. Those who are still
được phước báo lớn còn những người đang
on Rossi's path of detachment and non-attachment—that
đi trên con đường vô tâm vô sân của
is, those who haven't yet practiced the precepts—will receive
Rossi Tức là chưa tăng thực hành trai
great merit. For those who are still greedy, angry, and deluded and have
của mình lớn còn đối với đối tượng mà
n't yet practiced the
tham sân si chưa thực hành
Buddhist teachings,
ca cổ Phật thì mình cúng dường vào đó
the merit from their offerings will be small. Regarding my own situation, I have personally
Phước nhỏ cái gì trong cái phần của em
felt the spirits possessing
linh tự mình cảm nhận được các vong linh
me.
vào mình bị vong linh nhập tức là tự
I have practiced
mình cảm nhận được và em đã thực hành
according to the Buddha's teachings, cultivating
đúng lời Phật dạy là biết tu tập hồi
merit and dedicating it to the liberation of the spirits, so
hướng cầu siêu cho vong linh cho nên bây
now I am not possessed. Furthermore, on the
giờ em không bị vong linh nhập Nữa ngày
30th, 1st, and 14th of the lunar month, I have
30 mùng 1 vào 14 hôm rằm là em đã chấm
ended that practice, and my family life
dứt cái việc đó rồi và cuộc sống gia
is stable, my health has improved. This is what is
đình đã ổn định nên sức khỏe tốt lên thì
called the practice of transforming karma. I hope
thấy gọi là sự tu tập Chuyển Nghiệp mong
that all fellow practitioners will always diligently practice.
rằng các quỹ đạo hữu luôn luôn tinh tấn
Whatever suffering, through practice, it will transform everything. Dao Huu Ha
nhập Khổ gì Tu Tập cũng chuyển hóa cơ
The is called the
khí Đào Hữu hạ Thế gọi là Phật Pháp
miraculous power of the Buddha's teachings, and there are so many of them!
Nhiệm Mầu thật là nhiều vào à
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
Yeah yeah
ừ ừ
[Music]
[âm nhạc]